<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="anc.02138">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Documents Related to the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi></title> 
                <author>Brett Barney</author>
                <author>Stephanie Blalock</author>
                <author>Nicole Gray</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>anc.02138</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>The text encoding and content of this document was created and/or prepared by the <title level="m">Walt Whitman Archive</title> and is licensed under a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of these materials should credit the <title level="m">Walt Whitman Archive</title>.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                    <p>Written for <hi rend="italic">The Walt Whitman Archive</hi>. First published on the <hi rend="italic">Archive</hi> in 2020.</p> 
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2020-05-29" who="#smb">adding section on early draft advertisements</change>
            <change when="2019-09-06" who="#nhg">created file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="ancillary-variorum">
        <body>
            <head type="main">Documents Related to the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi></head>
            <div1 type="section"><p>A number of documents are important to understanding the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>, from the binder's receipt and copyright deposit page to a series of draft advertisements Whitman had printed. Here we provide images and a brief discussion of the context and significance of these documents. We also include a note about Whitman's desk copy, now held at the New York Public Library, into which he inserted manuscripts and drafts of material for later editions. In the future, we hope to provide more extensive editorial treatment of these items, including links to transcriptions.</p></div1>
            <div1 type="section" xml:id="production">
                <head type="sub">Production Documents</head>
                <p>Several surviving documents relate to the printing, binding, deposit, and sale of the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>. A binder's receipt written by Charles Jenkins shows copies bound in several stages. 
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="loc_js.00567.jpg"/>
                        <head>Figure.</head> 
                        <figDesc>Receipt for binding. Charles E. Feinberg Collection, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    The stages of binding listed in Jenkins's receipt include:<note xml:id="n1" type="authorial" resp="#nhg">Information about bindings has been supplemented by a transcription and explanation of this receipt in White and summaries in Winship and Myerson.</note> 
                    <list>
                        <item>June 1855: 200 copies at 32 cents each (probably cloth)</item>
                        <item>July 1855: 137 copies at 58 cents each (probably cloth) and 46 copies in "boards mounted" at 18 cents each</item>
                        <item>December 1855: 169 copies in cloth at 22 cents each and 150 copies in paper at 2 cents each</item>
                        <item>January 1856: 93 copies in "cloth plain" at 22 cents each</item>
                    </list></p>
                    <p>Bindings in June and July 1855 were probably state A, with gilt edges and goldstamped ornaments. Cloth bindings in December 1855 and January 1856 were probably state B, with blindstamped ornaments.<note xml:id="n2" type="authorial" resp="#nhg">This speculation is based on both the percentage of each state in surviving copies and the probable date of the reviews and extracts insertion, which was bound into some state B and state C copies. For more about the reviews and extracts, see the introduction to the variorum. For a complete list of binding states, see Winship and Myerson.</note> Jenkins, a Brooklyn bookbinder, evidently shifted the job to Davies &amp; Hands after the first round of (cloth-bound) copies. Jenkins wrote the following note to Whitman on the receipt: "You will see that I have charged you only 32 cts for the Leaves bound by me. The amount of the bill of Davies &amp; Hands over what it would have been at the same price is only about $30. They are not in condition to be able to let their accounts lay uncollected without embarrassment, and my means are invested so that the money is actually needed." Based on this receipt, scholars have concluded that 795 was likely the total number of copies printed (White, "The First," 353).</p>
                <p>Whitman deposited the book in the U.S. copyright office on May 15, 1855. Michael Winship has noted that the type used for the deposit title page differed from the type used for the title page in published copies.
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="loc_nhg.01000.jpg"/>
                        <head>Figure.</head> 
                        <figDesc>Title page for copyright deposit. Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                 <figure>
                     <graphic url="ppp.00271.008.jpg"/>
                     <head>Figure.</head>
                     <figDesc>Title page from copy of the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>, with different type used for the word "of." University of Iowa Special Collections and University Archives.</figDesc>
                 </figure>
                </p>
                <p>In 1956, Charles Feinberg located a draft of the copyright statement printed in most copies of the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> in a Whitman scrapbook in his collection. In research for a short article describing the discovery, William White determined that the document was written in the hand of George F. Betts, a clerk of the Southern District of New York, who processed Whitman's copyright deposit (White, "More About," 516). 
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="loc_js.00568.jpg"/>
                        <head>Figure.</head> 
                        <figDesc>Charles E. Feinberg Collection, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</figDesc>
                    </figure></p>
                    <p>White also identified the "Mr. Willmarth" whose name is written on the document in Whitman's hand as "Abel C. Willmarth, an attorney and clerk of the U.S. District Court," who Whitman may have known or gone to see for more information about the deposit ("More About," 516).</p>
                
            </div1>
            
                <div1 type="section">
                <head type="sub">Proofs of Reviews and Extracts</head>
                <p>Whitman arranged for the printing of an eight-page section devoted to reviews of the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>. He bound this section into several copies of the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>. Some copies have partial proofs of these reviews laid in.
                    
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="loc_nhg.01452.jpg"/>
                        <head>Figure. Proof version of "Walt Whitman, A Brooklyn Boy."</head> 
                        <figDesc>Charles E. Feinberg Collection, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="loc_nhg.01455.jpg"/>
                        <head>Figure. Proof version of "An English and An American Poet."</head> 
                        <figDesc>Charles E. Feinberg Collection, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="loc_nhg.01453.jpg"/>
                        <head>Figure. Proof version of extracts from <hi rend="italic">Putnam's Magazine</hi> review.</head> 
                        <figDesc>Charles E. Feinberg Collection, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</figDesc>
                    </figure></p>
            </div1>
            
            <!--At some point Whitman arranged for the printing of a series of what probably were intended to be draft advertisements for 
                    the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>. He must have done this while he was still revising the poems, because 
                    one of them features draft lines from the first poem in the volume, in later editions titled "Song of Myself." For more 
                    about Whitman's lifelong practice of printing slips with poems or prose drafts, see Winship, Grossman, and Stallybrass.-->
            
            <div1 type="section" xml:id="ads">
                <head type="sub">Early Draft Advertisements</head>
                <p>
                    Sometime before Whitman published the first edition of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> in 1855, he arranged for the printing of a series of 
                    draft advertisements for the volume that would introduce him as "The New Poet" and his book of verse as "America's first 
                    distinctive poem." These advertisements&#8212;four in total&#8212;range in length from six printed lines that succinctly 
                    describe the "green and gilt" physical appearance of the book and listed the price as &#36;1.50 to more than sixty printed 
                    lines of prose that offer an extended introduction to Whitman and his work. As far as we know, none of these early 
                    advertisements were published in mid-nineteenth-century newspapers or magazines exactly as they were printed here. A variation 
                    on the shortest advertisement&#8212;the least expensive to print&#8212;was published in New York newspapers in June and July of 1855. The 
                    three longest of these planned promotions included biographical information about the poet and/or several excerpts from his poems; however, 
                    Whitman's financial constraints likely prevented these advertisements from filling what would have been a substantial portion 
                    of a newspaper column. The poet, after all, financed the publication of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> (1855) himself and, without the backing 
                    of a publisher, did not have the additional funds required to mount an extensive promotional campaign for his book (Conrad 36). While 
                    these early promotional materials did not circulate among newspaper readers as Whitman had likely envisioned, they can significantly 
                    contribute to an understanding of the first edition of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>, and Whitman's continuing poetic project. An exploration of 
                    these advertisements offers insight into Whitman's early efforts to prepare, develop, and sustain a readership for his poetry. 
                    They illustrate his creative practices and his writing processes, including his work at drafting and revising, as well as his affinity 
                    for printing proofs or, as he called them, "slips" for revision and for promotional purposes.<note xml:id="n3" type="authorial" resp="#smb">
                        For more information on Whitman's practice of setting up poems in type so he could see how they looked
                        in addition to making editorial corrections, and on his ordering of multiple copies of proofs or what
                        he called "slips," see Peter Stallybrass, "Walt Whitman's Slips: Manufacturing Manuscript," <hi rend="italic">Walt
                            Whitman Quarterly Review</hi> 37.1 (Summer/Fall 2019): 66&#8211;106).</note>  These drafts 
                    not only show his frequent reuse of previously composed text in a variety of forms, but they may also 
                    represent a continuation of promotional strategies learned and applied during Whitman's career as a fiction writer, more than a 
                    decade prior, in the early 1840s.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="loc_ej.00403.jpg"/>
                        <head>Figure A.</head> 
                        <figDesc>Charles E. Feinberg Collection, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>
                  The shortest of the early draft advertisements for <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> (See Figure A) begins with the headline "The New Poet,"
                  three words that serves as a literary catchphrase, signaling the way in which Whitman wanted potential readers to think of him and his 
                  "distinctive" poetry. Only later in the advertisement, two lines below the headline, would the identity of the author of "Leaves of Grass" be revealed 
                  as "Walt Whitman." In doing so, this ad functions as a brief preview of the experience of opening Whitman's book for the first time. 
                  Readers who picked up the "green and gilt" volume of <hi rend="italic">Leaves</hi>, after all, would have encountered a title page from which the author's
                  name is conspiculously absent, as well as a frontispiece engraving of a man in work clothes and a hat with one hand positioned almost defiantly
                  on his hip, before seeing the author listed as "Walter Whitman" in the copyright statement or being introduced to the poetic persona as "Walt Whitman, an American,
                  one of the roughs, a kosmos," twenty-nine pages into the work. At the same time, this version of the advertisement suggests that Whitman 
                  was well aware that his unconventional poetry, "America's first distinctive poem," would not be readily legible to readers, buyers, or booksellers.
                  Even in these succinct lines, Whitman instructs his audience in how to approach the text, preparing them for poetic verse that will be different
                  from that they may encountered previously in newspapers or in other published volumes. The phrase "America's first distinctive poem" at once attests to 
                  the novelty of the poetry published by a "New Poet" and seems to encourage readers to see "Leaves of Grass" as a single poem 
                  that encompasses the entire volume. Given this draft advertisement's brevity and functionality, it is not surprising that it became the basis for
                  a "more subdued variation" or an even more affordable version that would be published in at least two New York newspapers
                  just prior to and shortly after the publication of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> (1855) (Conrad 33).</p>
                    
                  <p>On June 29, 1855, an advertisement similar to the above draft, but without the headline declaring Whitman "A New Poet" and without the phrase "America's first
                  distinctive poem" was published in the 
                  <hi rend="italic">Brooklyn Daily Eagle</hi>, a newspaper Whitman had edited from 1846 to 1848. The edited and published version read as follows: 
                   "Walt Whitman's Poems, 'Leaves of Grass,' 1 vol. small quarto: price &#36;2. For sale by W. W. Swayne, 210 Fulton st.
                   And at the other Brooklyn bookstores."<note xml:id="n4" type="authorial" resp="#smb">For the advertisment, 
                   see: <hi rend="italic">The Brooklyn Daily Eagle</hi>, June 29, 1855, pg. 3).</note> Ezra Greenspan located another version of this "brief and 
                   unpretentious" advertisement on the front page of Horace Greeley's <hi rend="italic">New York Tribune</hi> on July 6, 1855, which 
                   indicated that Whitman's book was for sale by both "Swayne" and "Fowlers &#38; Wells" at their establishment on Broadway in New York (91). 
                   "Swayne" was William Whiting Swayne of Ireland (ca. 1825&#8211;1883), a bookseller and, later, a publisher in Brooklyn, and the
                   firm of Fowler and Wells would become the publisher of Whitman's second edition of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> the following year, in 1856.
                   Less than a week after the advertisement ran in these newspapers, Swayne had his name removed from both, and each version continued to be published without his name 
                   in their respective papers. But Whitman did not lose sight of the preferred phrasing that was omitted from the advertisements for the 1855 edition that did make it into print. 
                   Whitman returned to the content of his unpublished draft advertisement five years later, when the third edition of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>
                   was published by the Boston firm of Thayer &#38; Eldridge. The description of Whitaman's volume as 
                   "America's First Distinctive Poem," a phrase that appeared at the start of the advertisements for the third edition
                      that ran in the <hi rend="italic">New-York Daily Tribune</hi>, were taken directly from Whitman's promotional material 
                      of 1855 (Conrad 37).<note xml:id="n5" type="authorial" resp="#smb">See for example, the advertisement for "America's First Distinctive Poem," 
                      Walt Whitman's Leaves of Grass," <hi rend="italic">New-York Daily Tribune</hi>, April 24, 1860, 1.</note> 
                   That Whitman revived and reused these words when he had the financial backing of Thayer &#38; Eldridge suggests that this particular way
                   of presenting <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> to potential readers was important to his continuing poetic project and to cultivating the readership he
                   envisioned for his poetry.</p>
            <p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="loc_ej.00405.jpg"/>
                    <head>Figure B.</head> 
                    <figDesc>Charles E. Feinberg Collection, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</figDesc>
                </figure>
            </p>
                <p> 
                    This draft advertisement (See Figure B) introduces Walt Whitman as a writer who "dashes full grown into literature," an apt
                    description in words of the effect of the frontispiece engraving from the 1855 edition of <hi rend="italic">Leaves</hi> in which the 
                    author seems to emerge from the page as "one good shaped" man.<note xml:id="n6" type="authorial" resp="#smb">See Whitman's Preface to the 1855 Edition of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>.</note>
                    The idea of "The New Poet," having just published his first book of verse, emerging on the literary 
                    scene, already established enough to be considered "dash[ing] full grown into literature," echoes the language of newspaper
                    advertisements for Whitman's first novel <hi rend="italic">Franklin Evans, or The Inebriate: A Tale of the Times</hi> (1842). Published thirteen 
                    years earlier in Park Benjamin's newspaper, <hi rend="italic">The New World</hi>, Whitman's potboiler temperance novel was 
                    promoted as a tale from "one of the best novelists in this country" and a work by "a Popular American Author."<note xml:id="n7" type="authorial" resp="#smb">See, for example, 
                     "New Works in Press," <hi rend="italic">The New World</hi>, November 19, 1842, Issue 21, 337.</note>
                    Whether the characterization of Whitman as a popular novelist was his own or a newspaper editor's, the rhetorical effect 
                    is similar to that of this draft advertisement insofar as here, Whitman, "the new poet," enters the literary scene already establishing a repuation for himself by 
                    laying claim in print, to being a fully developed and popular writer, as well as a self-proclaimed "bard of the masses."
                    </p>  
                <p>
                   Early in this advertisement, Whitman emphasizes his poetic process and creative practices, characterizing himself as a poet
                   and a craftsman, calling himself "this workman that perpetually builds with materials out of himself." He goes on to 
                   declare that he "surrounds his work with every character in nature, agriculture, art, books, household-life," as well
                   as the "life of the city streets" and "of the country." This passage suggests the kind of poetry that a reader of <hi rend="italic">Leaves</hi>
                   will encounter, preparing them for a poetic persona that assumes the form of "every character" and an author
                   whose work puts into printed characters the vocabulary of the science and art, as much as it does that of the "streets and wharves."
                   In addition to serving as an introduction to his writing, this advertisement focuses on the importance of Whitman's biography, outlining
                   his Long Island upbringing and his lived experience in New York. He is presented as having American heritage and a long line of ancestors with "untamed 
                   Anglo Saxon blood." But as signficant as that familial tradition and heritage might be, Whitman's writing is anything but 
                   traditional or conventional, an important distinction for readers soon to peruse Whitman's long lines that usually lacked
                   rhyme and meter. Whitman's understanding of lineage and ancestors does not, however, simply stretch into the past; he also
                   envisions himself as a forefather of a new generation of poets that, upon looking back, will recognize and acknowledge him
                   as an ancestor, a predecessor to their own creative processes, and a writer who shared with them the work of growing and furthering
                   a distinctive American poetry. After describing what readers can expect from his background and his style of writing, Whitman lays out expectations
                   for his readership. He instructs them in how to read <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>, explaining "you do not follow them
                   as reading a book, but as a willing and normal movement of you the reader. Whitman contrasts the passivity of observing and 
                   following with the far more active processes of enthusaism and "movement" in the act of reading, which seems to be an early version
                   of the concept of the athletic and even gymnastic reader that Whitman would try to instill in his audience.</p> 
                   
                  <p>Whitman includes some of the ideas and phrasing from this unpublished draft advertisement in a self-review for the 1855 
                   <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> entitled "Walt Whitman and His Poems," which was published in the September 1855 issue
                   of <hi rend="italic">The United States Review.</hi><note xml:id="n8" type="authorial" resp="#smb">See
                   Walt Whitman, "<ref target="https://whitmanarchive.org/criticism/reviews/lg1855/anc.00176.html">Walt Whitman and His Poems</ref>," 
                  <hi rend="italic">The United States Review</hi> 5 (September 1855), 205&#8211;212.</note> In both the advertisement, and the 
                  review, Whitman discusses the poets of the future; the advertisement notes that in Whitman, the United States have "come to their poetic voice" 
                  and that the poet "disclaims originality in his work, and announces the coming after him of a great breed of poets." According to Whitman, 
                  he is responsible for "the lifting of the baton to give the signal." In the self-review, Whitman writes a slightly different version 
                  of the same ideas, explaining "Walt Whitman himself disclaims singularity in his work, and announces
                  the coming after him of a great succession of poets, and the he but lifts his finger to give the signal." Whitman may have
                  returned to the unpublished advertisement to preserve the image of Whitman as the literary ancestor of future 
                  poets by inserting it into a promotional self-review that would reach periodical readers.</p>
                <p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="loc_ej.00404.jpg"/>
                        <head>Figure C.</head> 
                        <figDesc>Charles E. Feinberg Collection, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>This advertisment, announces the entrance of Walt Whitman, "An American Poet at last!" 
                (See Figure C) and highlights Whitman's understanding of himself as a "Kosmos Poet"
                whose poetic contributions "envelop[e] all partial and sectional ideas" (Conrad 33&#8211;34).
                According to the advertisement, this poet is best defined by poetic lines that catalog
                the various identities he references and assumes in <hi rend="italic">Leaves</hi>, listing
                him as "a northerner," "a planter," "A Louisianian," and a "Comrade of Californians," just
                to name a few. This selection of Whitman's poetry, spanning twenty-eight
                printed lines, constitutes a early version of a section of the 1855 poem that would eventually
                be titled "Song of Myself," which appears on pages twenty-three and twenty-four of the first
                edition. Whitman may have composed this advertisement using a manuscript version of the poem,
                and, then had the advertisment printed, such that it functioned as a proof for future 
                revisions (Conrad 35). Those changes included revisions in spelling ("Hoozier" in the advertisement, for example, becomes
                "Hoosier" in <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>) and the correction of a glaring typographical 
                error in Whitman's phrase "A northerner as soon as a northerner" in the first line of the poetic
                excerpt of the advertisement. In the first edition, this line is corrected to express the inclusionary
                sentiment that was intended so that Whitman becomes "A southerner soon as a northerner."
                Whitman also condenses the line from the advertisement that specifies the names of the Great Lakes, 
                "A boatman over Ontraio, Erie, Michigan, or Champlain" to the more encompassing line from
                the first edition that reads: "A boatman over the lakes or bays or along coasts." He goes
                on to make an addition to the line in the advertisement that reads "Not merely of the New
                World, but of Africa, Europe, or Asia," appending an ellipsis and the phrase "a wandering savage"
                to the line, following the word "Asia" in the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves</hi>.</p>
                
                <p>While this advertisement may be "the first if not the lone proof" Whitman had made 
                as he revised this section for inclusion in the 1855 edition of <hi rend="italic">Leaves</hi> (Conrad 35),
                Whitman reused very little of this advertisement in his self-reviews. Whitman does, however, return to the
                headline, "An American Poet at Last," altering the phrase slightly, to "An American Bard at Last," which
                he uses as the opening line for "Walt Whitman and His Poems" in the <hi rend="italic">The United States Review</hi>.
                In doing so, Whitman is preserving a catchphrase or a literary tag line, much like "The New Poet,"
                that could help readers identify remember him and his vision for his American and democratic poetic project.
                </p>      
            <p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="loc_ej.00406.jpg"/>
                        <head>Figure D.</head> 
                        <figDesc>Charles E. Feinberg Collection, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
            </p>
                <p>With a heading that simply reads "Walt Whitman," this draft advertisement (See Figure D) opens by asserting
                 Whitman as the poet of "mechanics and farmers" and as the poet of "women," a writer who "treats
                 the equality of the sexes as an insuperable truth of the universe." What follows this assertion of
                 Whitman as the poet of men and women equally is a lengthy block of prose that consists of phrases
                 separated by dashes, with what appears to be its own title, "The Poem of Men and Women." According
                 to the final sentence of the advertisement, these phrases are to be read as "foreshadowing hints, 
                 serving merely to introduce the twelve poems [of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> (1855)] to the reader."
                 This introduction to Whitman's writing prepares the reader for several structural aspects of encountering
                 his poems in the first edition. Reading long phrases separated by dashes as a block of prose that are subsumed
                 under a title that promises a poem becomes an example of the experience of encountering Whitman's 
                 long poetic lines that at first glance appear more like prose than poetry in his first edition. Taken together,
                 these phrases presenting the pilot, the carpenter, and the flatboatman among others, preview the
                 distinctive catalogs or lists of people, places, and objects that readers can find in a particular poem. 
                 The poet, the advertisement promises, actually "becomes"&#8212;through his verse&#8212;each of the characters he 
                 mentions in the list. Some of the "characters" mentioned here in the advertisement would be readily recognizable to a reader 
                 encountering a more extended consideration of them in <hi rend="italic">Leaves</hi>. For example, "the child uttering
                 fancies about the grass" in the advertisement serves as a "foreshadowing hint" to the inquisitive child who asks "What 
                 is the grass?" the first poem in Whitman's book, a poem that would later be titled "Song of Myself." In other cases,
                 the phrases presented in the advertisements or slight variations of them actually appear in the poem, although most often 
                 punctuated with commas an ellipses rather than dashes. "[T]he Missourian crossing the plains with his wares
                 and his 40 cattle" in the advertisement is "The Missourian crosses the plains toting his wares and his cattle"
                 in Whitman's volume. Almost all of the "hints" presented in the advertisement are referencing sections
                 of the poem later titled "Song of Myself" between pages twenty and twenty-four of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> (1855), especially
                 the parts of the poem that will later be numbered as Sections 15 and 16.
                 In addition to sharing phrases with the 1855 edition, this advertisement may also foreshadow the second edition of <hi rend="italic">Leaves</hi> given
                 Whitman's use of the title "The Poem of Men and Women," is very similar to his approach
                 to each of the poems in the 1856 edition, in which the title of each poem begins with the words "Poem of . . ."</p>
                 <p>
                 Whitman's preview of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> (1855), with its catalog of characters, separated by 
                 dashes not only includes words or phrases found in the first edition, but Whitman also reuses a portion of
                 the advertisement text in a self-review titled "An English and An American Poet," which was published in 
                 <hi rend="italic">American Phrenological Journal</hi> in October 1855.<note xml:id="n9" type="authorial" resp="#smb">
                 For the review, see "<ref target="https://whitmanarchive.org/criticism/reviews/lg1855/anc.00014.html">An English and 
                 American Poet</ref>," <hi rend="italic">American Phrenological Journal</hi>
                 22 (October 1855): 90&#8211;91.</note> Whitman's catalog of poetic references to the first edition, 
                 beginning with "the child uttering facies about the grass" through "the traveler from the most distant 
                 and diverse"&#8212;about thirty lines of printed text&#8212;have been incorporated, with some
                 revisions, into the self-review. The revisions, including the correction of a typographical error, 
                 may suggest that this early advertisement functioned as a draft for the promotional self-review.
                </p>
                
                <p>
                    When Whitman envisioned these early draft advertisements as promotional material for his first
                    edition of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>, he imagined a newspaper readership 
                    willing to examine lengthy texts that would introduce him and offer a preview of his 
                    poems. Ideally, through these advertisements, potential readers of Whitman
                    would become familiar with him and his writing style in preparation for the experience of 
                    reading <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> (1855) (Conrad 33). Whitman also intended
                    to share with these readers his hope for the future of his poetic project, which
                    he believed would be instrumental in the development of future generations of American poets,
                    all of whom would one day look back to a shared common ancestor: Walt Whitman.
                    At the same time, these advertisements offer insight into Whitman's drafting, revising, and 
                    writing practices. In these advertisements, Whitman drafted poetic lines, sometimes moving
                    edited version of those lines into <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>; he even transplanted 
                    whole paragraphs into reviews of the volume that he composed himself in order to further 
                    promote his poetry. In having these advertisements printed, Whitman ensures that they
                    serve as proofs, or what he called "slips," allowing him to experiment with the way 
                    particular lines and phrases would look once they are set in type and to decide
                    upon needed corrections (Stallybrass 79).
                   </p>
                    <p>
                    However, these early advertisements may not be Whitman's first experiments in contextualizing 
                   or introducing his writing to prospective readers with the aim of boosting the sales of his literary 
                   works. On November 17, 1842, the <hi rend="italic">New York Sun</hi>
                    published Whitman's short story "The Reformed" and prefaced the tale with the following note: "[We are 
                    permitted to extract the following beautiful sketch from a forthcoming novel, to be published next week 
                    at the New World office, called Franklin Evans, the Inebriate. It is written by Mr. Whitman, an author 
                    whose eloquent pen is in this work devoted to a most worthy cause&#8212;the cause of Temperance.]"<note
                   xml:id="n10" type="authorial" resp="#smb">For the publication history of "The Reformed,"
                   see "<ref target="https://whitmanarchive.org/published/fiction/shortfiction/anc.02090.html">About 'The Reformed.'"</ref></note>
                    The excerpted story functioned as a preview for Whitman's forthcoming novel, which gave readers a glimpse
                    of the novel's plot and introduced characters whose stories they might be eager to read and learn about. It
                    also worked to familiarize readers with the transition Whitman was making from a short fiction writer to
                    a novelist. Regardless of whether Whitman or the newspaper's editors choice the excerpted tale or made the
                    decisions to promote Whitman's first novel by preemptively declaring him "one of the best novelists in the country,"
                    Whitman would have seen and and understood this approach as a model for reaching prospective readers
                    and buyers of his literary works. By the time Whitman had these advertisements for <hi rend="italic">Leaves
                    of Grass</hi> (1855) printed and wrote his self-reviews of the volume, some thirteen years later, Whitman had likely given considerable 
                    thought to promotional strategies for his own work and for that of others given his considerable
                    experience as an editor of New York newspapers that published literature by a number of other writers.
                    It makes sense that Whitman would have used what he learned in his fiction career and in his 
                    editorial work to position his first volume of poetry as a distinctive and exciting project by
                    a new, yet already fully developed and successful poet with the potential to inspire generations
                    of readers and writers of poetry.</p>
                
                <p> Whitman certainly continued the practice of creating promotional and contextualzing materials for his works. He
                    published "Leaves-Droppings," for example, which included Ralph Waldo Emerson's famous
                    letter to the poet in praise of the first edition of <hi rend="italic">Leaves</hi>, as well as several critical 
                    responses to the 1855 edition, all of which were appended to the second (1856) edition
                    of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>. The self-reviews of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> (1855)
                    that were published in the <hi rend="italic">United States Review </hi>and the <hi rend="italic">American Phrenological Journal</hi>&#8212;both of 
                    which drew on these early advertisements&#8212;were included in "Leaves-Droppings."<note
                        xml:id="n11" type="authorial" resp="#smb">For more on "Leaves-Droppings,"
                        see John Reitz, "<ref target="https://whitmanarchive.org/criticism/current/encyclopedia/entry_28.html">'Leaves-Droppings' [1856],</ref>" J.R. LeMaster and Donald D. Kummings, eds., Walt Whitman: An Encyclopedia (New York: Garland Publishing, 1998).</note>
                    an advertisement for his journalistic series on diet and excercise, "Manly Health and Training" (1858), which was 
                    published in <hi rend="italic">The New York Atlas</hi> on September 12, 1858. Two years later, Whitman garnered
                    publicity for the third edition of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> by publishing a  
                    64-page promotional pamphelet, entitled, <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass Imprints</hi> that
                    included American and European criticisms of the two previously published edition of <hi rend="italic">Leaves</hi>, 
                    which also included the two aforementioned self-reviews.<note
                        xml:id="n12" type="authorial" resp="#smb">For more on <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass Imprints</hi>,
                        see Eric Conrad, "<ref target="https://whitmanarchive.org/published/LG/tei/imprintsintro.html">Introduction to <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass Imprints</hi></ref>".</note> Thus, while these early draft advertisements
                    remained unpublished as they are presented here, the phrases, exceprts of poems, and conceptions of <hi rend="italic">
                    Leaves of Grass</hi> they included, circulated in a varitey of forms, and have an important 
                    place in the range of promotional materials and strategies that Whitman utilized through
                    his literary career to garner the future generaions of lifelong readers and fans that
                    he imagined one hundred and sixty-five years ago.</p> 
                    
            </div1>
            <div1 type="section" xml:id="deskcopy">
                <head type="sub">Whitman's Desk Copy</head>
                <p>The New York Public Library has Whitman's desk copy of the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>, into which he pasted manuscripts and other documents.</p>
                <p><figure>
                    <graphic url=""/>
                    <head>Figure.</head> 
                    <figDesc>New York Public Library</figDesc>
                </figure></p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="bibliography">
                
                <head type="main-authorial">Bibliography</head>
                
                <listBibl>
                    
                    <bibl>Conrad, Eric. "The Walt Whitman Brand: <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> and Literary Promotion, 1855&#8211;1892.” 
                        Ph.D. Dissertation, University of Iowa, 2013.
                    </bibl> 
                    <bibl>Folsom, Ed. "Appearing in Print: Illustrations of the Self in <hi
                        rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>," <hi rend="italic">The 
                            Cambridge Companion to Walt Whitman</hi>, edited by Ezra Greenspan (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1995), 135&#8211;165.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Folsom, Ed. <hi rend="italic">Whitman Making Books / Books Making Whitman</hi>. Iowa City: Obermann Center for 
                        Advanced Studies, 2005.
                    </bibl>
                   
                    <bibl>Greenspan, Ezra. <hi rend="italic">Walt Whitman and the American Reader</hi>. New York: Cambridge 
                        University Press, 1990.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Grossman, Jay. "Manuprint." <hi rend="italic">Walt Whitman Quarterly Review</hi>, 37.1 (2019), 46&#8211;65.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Miller, Matt. <hi rend="italic">Collage of Myself: Walt Whitman and the Making of Leaves of Grass</hi> (Lincoln:
                    University of Nebraksa Press, 2010).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Morton, Heather. "Democracy, Self-Reviews and the 1855 <hi
                        rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>." <hi rend="italic">Virginia 
                            Quarterly Review</hi> (Spring 2005): 229&#8211;243. 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Myerson, Joel. <hi rend="italic">Walt Whitman: A Descriptive Bibliography</hi> (Pittsburgh: University of Pittsburgh Press, 1993), 12&#8211;22.</bibl>
                    <bibl>O’Driscoll, Michael J. "Whitman in the Archive: <hi rend="italic">Leaves
                        of Grass</hi> and the Culture of the 
                        Book." <hi rend="italic">English Studies in Canada</hi> 25(1999): 295&#8211;323.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Reynolds, David S. <hi rend="italic">Walt Whitman’s America</hi>. New York: Vintage Books, 1995.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Stallybrass, Peter. "Walt Whitman's Slips: Manufacturing Manuscript." <hi rend="italic">Walt Whitman Quarterly Review</hi>, 37.1 (2019), 66&#8211;106.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Traubel, Horace. <hi rend="italic">With Walt Whitman in Camden</hi>. Various publishers, 1906&#8211;1996.</bibl>
                    <bibl>White, William. "More About the 'Publication' of the First <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>." <hi rend="italic">American Literature</hi> 28.4 (1957): 516&#8211;17.</bibl>
                        <bibl>- - -. "The First (1855) 'Leaves of Grass': How Many Copies?" <hi rend="italic">Papers of the Bibliographical Society of America</hi> 57.3 (1963): 352&#8211;4.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Winship, Michael. "Walt Whitman." <hi rend="italic">Bibliography of American Literature</hi>, Vol. 9 (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1991), 31&#8211;2.</bibl>

                    
                </listBibl>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>