<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?> <?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="anc.02138">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Documents Related to the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi></title> 
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>anc.02138</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>The text encoding and content of this document was created and/or prepared by the <title level="m">Walt Whitman Archive</title> and is licensed under a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of these materials should credit the <title level="m">Walt Whitman Archive</title>.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>The Walt Whitman Archive</author>
                    <title>Documents Related to the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi></title>                  
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2019-09-06" who="#nhg">created</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="ancillary-variorum">
        <body>
            <head type="main">Documents Related to the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi></head>
            <div1 type="section"><p>A number of peripheral documents are important to understanding the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>, from the copyright deposit page to the binders' receipts to a series of draft ads Whitman had printed. Here we provide images and a brief discussion of the context and significance of these documents. In the future, we hope to provide more extensive editorial treatment of these documents, including links to transcriptions.</p></div1>
            <div1 type="section">
                <head type="sub">Production Documents</head>
                <p>A series of documents relate to the printing, binding, and deposit of the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>.</p>
                <p>The binder's receipt shows the number of books bound in Binding A. 
                    <figure facs="loc_js.00567_large.jpg"/></p>
                <p>This draft copyright notice for the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> is written in another hand.
                    <figure facs="loc_js.00568_large.jpg"/></p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="section">
                <head type="sub">Annotated Reviews</head>
                <p>Whitman annotated proofs and final versions of the reviews he had printed and bound into some copies of the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>.</p>
                <p>These annotations on this final version of the insertion did not make it into the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves</hi> version. [Did they make it into any other version?] 
                    <figure facs="loc_ej.00411_large.jpg"/>
                    <figure facs="loc_ej.00415_large.jpg"/>
                    <figure facs="loc_ej.00416_large.jpg"/></p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="section">
                <head type="sub">Autographed Frontispiece Prints</head>
                <p>A series of prints made of the frontispiece engraving are signed by Whitman in blue ink. Some of these are laid into copies of the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>.</p>
                <p><figure facs="Pa110927.jpg"/>
                    <figure facs="duk_nhg.00809_large.jpg"/>
                </p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="section">
                <head type="sub">Early Draft Advertisements</head>
                <p>At some point Whitman had printed a series of what appear to be draft advertisements for the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>. He must have done this while he was still revising the poems, because one of them features draft lines from what would become the first poem in the volume, in later editions titled "Song of Myself." For more about Whitman's printed slips, see Michael Winship, "Walt Whitman," <hi rend="italic">Bibliography of American Literature</hi>, Vol. 9 (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1991), 28-103; Jay Grossman, "Manuprint" (forthcoming in the <hi rend="italic">Walt Whitman Quarterly Review</hi>), and Peter Stallybrass, "Manufacturing Manuscript: Walt Whitman's 'Slips'" (forthcoming in the <hi rend="italic">Walt Whitman Quarterly Review</hi>).</p>
                <p><figure facs="loc_ej.00405_large.jpg"/>
                    <figure facs="loc_ej.00403_large.jpg"/>
                    <figure facs="loc_ej.00404_large.jpg"/>
                    <figure facs="loc_ej.00406_large.jpg"/></p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="section">
                <head type="sub">Whitman's Desk Copy</head>
                <p>The New York Public Library has Whitman's desk copy of the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>, into which he pasted manuscripts and other documents.</p>
                <p><figure facs=""/></p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>