<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="anc.02143">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Documents Related to the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>: Whitman's Copy</title> 
                <author>Brett Barney</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>file creation</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2020</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>anc.02143</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>The text encoding and content of this document were created and/or prepared by the <title level="m">Walt Whitman Archive</title> and is licensed under a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of these materials should credit the <title level="m">Walt Whitman Archive</title>.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                    <p>Written for <hi rend="italic">The Walt Whitman Archive</hi>. First published on the <hi rend="italic">Archive</hi> in 2020.</p> 
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2020-06-03" who="#bb">added content and encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-06-02" who="#nhg">created file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="ancillary-variorum">
        <body>
            
            <div1 type="section" xml:id="deskcopy">
                <head type="sub">Whitman's Copy of the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi></head>

                <p>Whitman's copy of the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>, into which he inserted a series of prose manuscripts, is now part of the Oscar Lion Collection at New York Public Library. One of four copies of the first edition in the Lion Collection, it is currently off-limits to researchers. Because of this, one must piece together information about it from the library's online catalog and from secondhand sources, including the work of Clifton Joseph Furness and Edward F. Grier, two earlier editors who had direct access to this unique copy and published editions of the manuscripts contained in it. The catalog entry (in which Whitman's copy is labelled simply "Copy 4") notes that the volume has "original pink paper covers" and contains "8 booklets of manuscripts, 52 leaves in all."<note xml:id="n1" type="authorial" resp="#bb">Grier counts eleven manuscripts, and Furness counts “seven separate notebooks” (117). Among the possible reasons for the discrepancies among these accounts are that 1) some of the items that Grier treats as separate consist of just one leaf and are apparently attached to other manuscript leaves rather than to printed pages; 2) although many of the gatherings are bound with ribbon or string, at least one is made up of papers of various sizes pinned together (see Grier 1484); and 3) Furness seems, in several cases, to have taken license in his representations of layout and disposition (see, e.g., Grier 1447, 1475).</note> The library has created digital images of the front cover and most (though apparently not all) of the manuscript pages.<note xml:id="n2" type="authorial" resp="#bb">From the links below we reproduce all of the images currently available, courtesy of Rare Book Division, The New York Public Library, <hi rend="italic">The New York Public Library Digital Collections</hi>. 1 &#124; 2 &#124; 3 &#124; 4 &#124; 5 &#124; 6 &#124; 7 &#124; 8 &#124; 9 &#124; 10 &#124; 11 &#124; 12 &#124; 13 &#124; 14 &#124; 15 &#124; 16 &#124; 17 &#124; 18 &#124; 19 &#124; 20 &#124; 21 &#124; 22 &#124; 23 &#124; 24 &#124; 25 &#124; 26 &#124; 27 &#124; 28 &#124; 29 &#124; 30 &#124; 31 &#124; 32 &#124; 33 &#124; 34 &#124; 35 &#124; 36 &#124; 37 &#124; 38 &#124; 39 &#124; 40 &#124; 41 &#124; 42 &#124; 43<!--<ref target="https://digitalcollections.nypl.org/collections/oscar-lion-collection#/?tab=navigation&amp;roots=23:1c1cf2e0-c5d9-012f-8920-58d385a7bc34">here</ref>--></note>
</p>

                <p><figure>
                    <graphic url="anc.02143_fig01.jpg"/>
                    <head>Figure.</head> 
                    <figDesc>Image of the paper front cover of Whitman's copy of the first edition of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>, as presented in the Digital Collection of New York Public Library.</figDesc>
                </figure></p>

<p>On the cover, below the title, Whitman has written, "2'd &amp; fullest version of original Edition / 1855–'56 / (the 1st edition consisted of the Poems alone—some months afterwards the extracts &amp;c. prefacing the text, as here, were added—making this edition)." Another note, in the hand of Horace Traubel, is written above the title. What is known about the history of Whitman's copy of the 1855 edition of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> comes from this note, from a brief mention in Traubel's <hi rend="italic">With Walt Whitman in Camden</hi>, and from a May 12, 1928, letter from Anne Montgomerie Traubel to Oscar Lion. According to the entry for February 15, 1889, in <hi rend="italic">With Walt Whitman in Camden</hi>, Whitman told Horace Traubel that he had kept "only one copy" of the first edition, that he didn’t at the time know where it was, and that he intended for Traubel "to have it when it reappear[ed]" (151). According to Anne Traubel, Whitman never did find the book; it was discovered only "several years after Whitman’s death," during the division of papers among his literary executors (Furness 118-119).</p> 

<p>The manuscripts in Whitman's copy of the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> vary in apparent completeness, as well as in tone and implied audience. All of them, however, are written in prose and can be fairly described as providing some sort of introduction to <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>. A few dates appear in the manuscripts, and these, along with other clues, suggested to Grier a range of dates during the 1860s. None of the manuscripts were published in Whitman's lifetime, though they share similarities with some of the poet's published statements, especially the introduction to <hi rend="italic">As a Strong Bird on Pinions Free</hi> (1872).<note xml:id="n3" type="authorial" resp="#bb">Furness classifies the manuscripts into "three principal clusters of material, one for an 'Introduction' . . . for <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>; another for an 'Inscription to the Reader at the Entrance of Leaves of Grass'; and a final record of Whitman’s own appraisal of his work, together with proposals for its continuance and extension" (120). He also speculates at some length upon Whitman's reasons for leaving them unpublished (see pp. 121–126).</note></p>  

<p>Unfortunately, both Furness and Grier focus almost exclusively on the manuscript material; neither provides much information about the printed book into which it is fastened. This silence&#8212;along with the lack of page images or other information in the New York Public Library catalog&#8212;leaves many basic questions about Whitman's copy of the first edition unanswerable at present.</p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="bibliography">
                
                <head type="main-authorial">Bibliography</head>
                
                <listBibl>

                    <bibl>Grier, Edward F. "Introductions to <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass,</hi>" <hi rend="italic">Notebooks and Unpublished Prose Manuscripts</hi> (New York: New York University Press, 1984), 4:1445&#8211;1490.</bibl>

                    <bibl>Furness, Clifton Joseph. "Introductions Intended or American Editions of 'Leaves of Grass,'" <hi rend="italic">Walt Whitman's Workshop</hi> (Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1928), 115&#8211;137.</bibl>
                    
                    <bibl>Traubel, Horace. <hi rend="italic">With Walt Whitman in Camden</hi>. Vol. 4, <hi rend="italic">January 21 to April 7, 1889.</hi> Edited by Sculley Bradley. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 1953.</bibl>
                    
                </listBibl>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>