<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="anc.02145">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Documents Related to the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>: Copyright Materials</title> 
                <author>Nicole Gray</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2020</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>anc.02145</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P. O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>The text encoding and content of this document was created and/or prepared by the <title level="m">Walt Whitman Archive</title> and is licensed under a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of these materials should credit the <title level="m">Walt Whitman Archive</title>.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Written for <hi rend="italic">The Walt Whitman Archive</hi>. First published on the <hi rend="italic">Archive</hi> in 2020.</p> 
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2020-06-16" who="#nhg">created file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="ancillary-variorum">
        <body>
            <div1 type="section" xml:id="production">
                <head type="sub">Copyright Materials</head>
                <p>Whitman registered the copyright for the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> in the clerk's office of the U.S. District Court for the Southern District of New York on May 15, 1855.<note xml:id="n6" type="authorial">Copyright was not centralized at the Library of Congress until 1870. For editions of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> published after that date, Whitman corresponded with Ainsworth Spofford, Librarian of Congress, about copyright registration. See Nierman and "Overview."</note> Copyright on the book was renewed on March 15, 1883, for fourteen additional years.<note xml:id="n7" type="authorial">Myerson, 18. For further discussion of Whitman's attention to copyright, see Buinicki.</note> Copies of the deposit title pages for this and later editions of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> are held in the Rare Books and Special Collections Division at the Library of Congress. Michael Winship has noted that the type used for the deposit title page differed from the type used for the title page in published copies.<note xml:id="n5" type="authorial"><hi rend="italic">Bibliography of American Literature</hi> papers. It is possible that the title page was set up and a few copies printed separately for this purpose.</note> 
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="loc_nhg.01000.jpg"/>
                        <head>Figure.</head> 
                        <figDesc>A copy of the title page used for copyright deposit. Rare Books and Special Collections Division, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. A note on the reverse of the leaf in an unidentified hand reads: "Filed May 15, 1855 / Walter Whitman / [au &amp; pro?]."</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="ppp.00271.008.jpg"/>
                        <head>Figure.</head>
                        <figDesc>Title page from copy of the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>, with different type used for the word "of." University of Iowa Special Collections and University Archives.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>In all but three of the known surviving copies of the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>, the copyright notice is printed in two lines on the verso of the title page. One Williams College copy has a blank copyright page; two other copies, now at the University of Virginia and the Providence Athen&#230;um, have the copyright notice written in Whitman's hand.<note xml:id="n3" type="authorial">See <ref target="../../bibliography/index.html#WC_02">WC_02</ref>, <ref target="../../bibliography/index.html#UVa_10">UVa_10</ref>, and <ref target="../../bibliography/index.html#PA_01">PA_01</ref>, respectively.</note> In 1956, Charles Feinberg located a handwritten draft of the copyright notice in a Whitman scrapbook in his collection.<note xml:id="n4" type="authorial">White notes by way of context that "the scrapbook was used by Whitman to keep clippings from newspapers and magazines," and that some items are dated in Whitman's hand: the dates range from 1844 to 1850 (516).</note> In research for a short article describing the discovery, William White determined that the document was written in the hand of George F. Betts, a clerk of the Southern District of New York, who processed Whitman's copyright deposit on May 15 (516). 
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="loc_nhg.01460.jpg"/>
                        <head>Figure.</head> 
                        <figDesc>Draft 1855 copyright statement. The penciled note ("Mr. Willmarth") is in Whitman's hand. Charles E. Feinberg Collection, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="loc_nhg.01461.jpg"/>
                        <head>Figure.</head> 
                        <figDesc>Reverse of draft 1855 copyright statement. Charles E. Feinberg Collection, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>White also identified the "Mr. Willmarth" whose name is written on the document in Whitman's hand as "Abel C. Willmarth, an attorney and clerk of the U.S. District Court," who Whitman may have known or gone to see for more information about the deposit (516). No information has yet been discovered about what Whitman's business may have been with the address, "58 Barclay," written on the reverse of the leaf.</p>
                
            </div1>
            
            <div1 type="bibliography">
                
                <head type="main-authorial">Bibliography</head>
                
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Bibliography of American Literature</hi> Papers, 1943&#8211;1991. Houghton Library, Harvard University. HH0376, box 26, BAL worksheets Whittier&#8211;Willis.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Buinicki, Martin T. "Walt Whitman and the Question of Copyright." <hi rend="italic">American Literary History</hi>, 15.2 (Summer 2003): 248&#8211;75.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Nierman, Judith. "Walt Whitman's <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>." <hi rend="italic">Copyright Lore</hi> (May 2005): 8.</bibl>
                    <bibl>"Overview of the Copyright Office." U.S. Copyright Office, n.d. https://www.copyright.gov/about.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Myerson, Joel. <hi rend="italic">Walt Whitman: A Descriptive Bibliography</hi> (Pittsburgh: University of Pittsburgh Press, 1993), 12&#8211;22.</bibl>
                    
                    <bibl>White, William. "More About the 'Publication' of the First <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>." <hi rend="italic">American Literature</hi> 28.4 (1957): 516&#8211;17.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Winship, Michael. "Walt Whitman." <hi rend="italic">Bibliography of American Literature</hi>, Vol. 9 (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1991), 31&#8211;2.</bibl>
                    
                    
                </listBibl>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
